<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The speech of the right honourable Edward, Earl of Manchester, Lord Chamberlain of His Majesties houshold delivered at the Guild-Hall, London, on Thursday, being the first day of December, 1664. at a common hall there held : where were also present ... members of the honourable Houses of Parliament.</title>
            <author>Manchester, Edward Montagu, Earl of, 1602-1671.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89463</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M398A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42584</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">36282382</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 36282382</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150122</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89463)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150122)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2231:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The speech of the right honourable Edward, Earl of Manchester, Lord Chamberlain of His Majesties houshold delivered at the Guild-Hall, London, on Thursday, being the first day of December, 1664. at a common hall there held : where were also present ... members of the honourable Houses of Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Manchester, Edward Montagu, Earl of, 1602-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 [i.e. 7] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh,</pubPlace>
                  <date>Re-printed, 1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained and tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Error in paging: p. 7 mis-numbered 4.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Expenditures, Public --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History, Naval --  Stuarts, 1603-1714.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150122:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SPEECH Of the right Honourable EDWARD EARL of <hi>MANCHESTER,</hi> Lord Chamberlain of His MAJESTIES HOUSHOLD.</p>
            <p>Delivered at the <hi>Guild-Hall London,</hi> on Thurſday, being the firſt day of <hi>December,</hi> 1664. at a Common Hall there held.</p>
            <p>Where were alſo preſent
<list>
                  <item>The Earl of <hi>Bridgewater.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord Biſhop of <hi>London.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Berkley</hi> of <hi>Berkley.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Moone.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Lord <hi>Aſhley</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Vice-Chamberlain.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. Secretary <hi>Bennet.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Viſcount <hi>Cornebury.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Thomas Clifford.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Colonel <hi>Popham.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Waller.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Colonel <hi>Fretzvile.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Philip Warwick.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>John Berkenhead.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Aſhburnham.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>George Reeve.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>William Lowther.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Members of the honourable Houſes of Parliament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINBURGH,</hi> Re-printed, 1664.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:150122:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>C R</head>
                  <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:150122:2"/>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="speech">
                        <head>THE SPEECH Of the Right Honourable, EDWARD, Earle of <hi>MANCHESTER,</hi> Lord Chamberlain of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> Houſehold. Delivered at the <hi>Guild-Hall, London,</hi> on <hi>Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> the firſt of <hi>December,</hi> 1664. at the Common Hall there held, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </head>
                        <opener>
                           <salute>My Lord Mayor, and Aldermen, and you the worth Citizens of this great and famous City of <hi>London.</hi>
                           </salute>
                        </opener>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Hope our coming hither this day, and upon this occaſion, will be as ſatisfactory to you, as it is gratefull to us: Some of us have formerly addreſſed our ſelves unto you, by His Majeſties Command, for the Loan of ſeveral and great ſummes of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150122:3"/>Money, and we found ſuch a ready compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with His Majeſties deſires, as we can give teſtimony to the Nation, that in your duty and affection to your King, you have out-done all other Cities, even the greateſt Cities of the Chriſtian World; and let this honour remain with you, and be entailed to your poſterities for ever.</p>
                        <p>But we come not now to ask, but to give a return of thanks, hearty thanks, from the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for your forwardneſs in aſſiſting the King.</p>
                        <p>What you intended as a private and perſonal duty and kindneſs to your King, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment owns as a publick ſervice to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and that upon a juſt account: For His Majeſty borrowed not theſe ſummes to convert them to His private expences, but to employ them for publick uſe, to prepare and ſet forth a Fleet, able to conteſt for victory againſt all the naval powers of His inſulting and injurious Neighbours: And in order to this deſign, His Majeſty hath impaired His own Stock, by exhauſting His own Stores; He hath improved his own Induſtry, and not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150122:3"/>ſpared His own Perſonal Labour and Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence: and to compleat and perfect this De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, His Royal Highneſs, His Majeſties dear and only Brother, hath expoſed Himſelf to hazzard and danger. And this Prince is of ſuch an accompliſhed Gallantry, that, through the bleſſing of God, you need not queſtion a happy Succeſs under ſo good a Conduct.</p>
                        <p>All this His Majeſty hath done as the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of His Country, not conſulting His own Intereſt, but for the Honour of the Nation, and to ſecure and advance the Trade and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce of His Kingdoms, in which this City hath ſo eminent a concernment and advantage, as probably we may conclude this Propheſie will not only be fitly applied, but truly fulfilled in your dayes, unto the City of <hi>London; The Harveſt of the Rivers is Her Revenue, and ſhe is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Mart of Nations.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Thus you ſee the happineſs and advantage of living under ſuch a King, whoſe generous nature prompts Him to remember and to acknowledge benefits, as well as to receive them.</p>
                        <p>His Majeſty declares to the Parliament what the City of <hi>London</hi> had done for Him, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150122:4"/>what He had done for the Safety and Honour of the Kingdom, by their kind and cheerfull aſſiſtance; and expreſſes Himſelf in ſuch a phraſe, as makes you partners with Him in all the happy conſequences of this great Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
                        <p>The Parliament having received this account from the mouth of their King, return you their Thanks, with the full conſent and the unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Votes of both Houſes, the Lords and Commons, which I here deliver to you as a Record of their acknowledgements of your Services done to the King.</p>
                        <p>And now give me leave to offer our Well-wiſhes to you, That this City may never want the Favour, Countenance, and Protection of ſuch a King; and that His Majeſty may alwayes finde the Fidelity, Affection, and Aſſiſtance of ſuch a City.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:150122:4"/>
And after a great Shout of <hi>GOD SAVE THE KING,</hi> the Lord Chamberlain having preſented to the Right Honourable the LORD MAIOR an order of both Houſes of Parliament, the ſame was delivered to Mr. <hi>Avery,</hi> Deputy Town-Clerk, who then publickly read the ſame, and follows in theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="speech">
                        <opener>
                           <dateline>
                              <date>Die Veneris, 25 <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1664.</date>
                           </dateline>
                        </opener>
                        <p>ORDERED by the Lords Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Temporal, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in Parliament aſſembled, That the Thanks of both Houſes of Parliament be given unto the City of <hi>LONDON</hi> for their forwardneſs in aſsiſting His Majeſty; and in particular, by furniſhing Him with ſeveral great ſummes of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney toward His Preparations for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, Safety, and Trade of this Nation.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>
                              <hi>Jo. Browne,</hi> Cleric. Parliament.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> Reprinted, 1664.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150122:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
